<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:w="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/"
	xmlns:xht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#"
>
	<head>
		<meta charset="UTF-8" />
		<title>HTTP REPORT</title>
		<meta name="description" content="Request a transfer of the target resource" />
		<link rel="up" href="index.xml"/>
	</head>
	<body>
		<main about="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/http/methods/REPORT" typeof="w:HTTP-Method">
			<a rel="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#describedby" href=""></a>

			<h1>REPORT</h1>
			<p>Generates a response to a payload. Unlike POST, this method is safe; and unlike GET, a request body must be supported. Initially defined for WebDAV, this method is usable by any application where a client needs to submit a document to the server with a safe method (that will not change the server state).</p>
			<p>See <a href="../query.xml">Queries in HTTP</a> for alternative methods of implementing server-evaluated queries.</p>

			<h2>Writing requests (clients)</h2>
			<p>Clients may use the REPORT method when it sees <code>Allow: REPORT</code> in a response; when a form specifies a query may be submitted using the REPORT method; or when there is out-of-band knowledge that the resource supports it.</p>
			<aside><p>Presently, no known hypermedia formats specifically support the REPORT method. However, it seems feasible to specify <code>REPORT</code> in any place <code>POST</code> would be an acceptable value.</p></aside>

			<h2>Reading requests (servers)</h2>
			<p>Servers should implement REPORT when there is a possibility that a GET query would be or cause performance problems. REPORT is not known to be well supported, and servers should implement alternate mechanisms of making a query (see <a href="../query.xml">Queries in HTTP</a>).</p>
			<p>Servers that support REPORT on a resource should list so in an <a href="../headers/Allow.xml">Allow response header</a>, and a GET response should describe how to format and make the request.</p>

			<h2>Example</h2>
			<p>First, the client makes a request:</p>
			<pre w:space="indent">
				REPORT /query HTTP/1.1
				Content-Type: application/json

				{ "id": { "$gt": 200 } }
			</pre>
			<p>The server evaluates the query according to the semantics of the resource and content type, and generates a response:</p>
			<pre w:space="indent">
				HTTP/1.1 200 OK
				Content-Type: application/json

				{
					"recordset": [
						{"id": 100, "name": "root"},
						{"id": 1000, "name":"Alice"},
						{"id": 1001, "name":"Bob"}
					]
				}
			</pre>

			<h2>Overview table</h2>
			<dl>
				<dt>Name</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Header-name">REPORT</dd>
				<dt>Description</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Method-description">Generates a response to a payload.</dd>
				<dt>Specification</dt>
				<dd property="w:specification"><a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3253#section-3.6">RFC 3253: Versioning Extensions to WebDAV &#xA7;3.6: REPORT Method</a></dd>
			</dl>
		</main>
	</body>
</html>
