<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:w="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/"
	xmlns:xht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#"
>
	<head>
		<meta charset="UTF-8" />
		<title>Accept-Encoding</title>
		<meta name="description" content="The Accept-Encoding HTTP request-header specify response content codings that are acceptable to the user-agent." />
		<link rel="up" href="index.xml" />
	</head>
	<body>
		<main id="main-content" about="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/http/headers/Accept-Encoding" typeof="w:HTTP-Header">
			<a rel="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#describedby" href="" />

			<h1>Accept-Encoding</h1>
			<p>The Accept-Encoding header specifies which response content codings are acceptable to the client.</p>
			<p>This header is typically used to indicate the user agent supports compressed response messages, such as gzip.</p>

			<h2>Usage in requests</h2>
			<h3>Writing requests (clients)</h3>
			<p>Write an Accept-Encoding header listing which content codings that the user-agent is capable of decoding, especially compression methods. Check the response <a href="Content-Encoding.xml">Content-Encoding header</a> to determine how to decode the message body, if necessary.</p>

			<h3>Reading requests (servers)</h3>
			<p>Using the Accept-Encoding header to select a response content coding is not trivial; keep a mapping of supported content-codings to available encoders or encoded representations, and use a library to match the incoming Accept-Encoding to an available encoding. If more than one representation could be selected from, add a <a href="Vary.xml">Vary header</a> of <code>Vary: Accept-Encoding</code> to indicate to caches that the response might vary based on this header.</p>
			<p>For HTTP/Web applications, consider using a transforming HTTP gateway or cache to perform this step, instead of adding this complexity in the application.</p>
			<!-- TODO: link to list of content codings -->


			<h2>Usage in responses</h2>
			<p>RFC 7231 only specifies the request form of this header. RFC 7694 specifies usage in a response to indicate the client's selected content coding is not understood, and the client may re-make the request with one of the listed content codings.</p>

			<h3>Writing responses (servers)</h3>
			<p>Servers send Accept-Encoding to the client in <a href="../status-codes/415.xml">415 Unsupported Media Type</a> responses. The header could also be sent in response to OPTIONS.</p>
			<p>The server should first ensure the resource exists, that the user-agent has the proper credentials to make the request, and any other checks that can be performed without needing to know the exact details of the request-body.</p>
			<p>If the server receives a request from a client with a <a href="Content-Encoding.xml">Content-Encoding value</a> that it does not understand, send <code>415 Unsupported Media Type</code> with an <code>Accept-Encoding</code> header listing the content codings the server can accept from clients.</p>
			<p>The 415 Unsupported Media Type status can be used for other purposes (e.g. an invalid Content-Type), do not supply this header in these other cases.</p>

			<h3>Reading responses (clients)</h3>
			<p>Reading the Accept-Encoding header is only necessary from a response with <code>415 Unsupported Media Type</code>. In this case, the client should re-make the request with one of the listed content codings listed in the response <code>Accept-Encoding</code> header.</p>
			<p>Clients who would like to handle this error before writing the request body should send <code>Expect: 100-continue</code>. See the <a href="Content-Encoding.xml">Content-Encoding header</a> for information about how to make requests with a content encoding.</p>

			<h2>Overview table</h2>
			<dl class="inline">
				<dt>Name</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Header-name">Accept-Encoding</dd>
				<dt>Description</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Header-description">Specifies which response content codings are acceptable.</dd>
				<dt>Direction</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Header-direction">Both</dd>
				<dt>Negotiates</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Header-negotiates" resource="w:http/headers/Content-Encoding"><a href="Content-Encoding.xml">Content-Encoding</a></dd>
				<dt>List usage in</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Header-list-in" resource="w:http/headers/Vary"><a href="Vary.xml">Vary</a></dd>
				<dt>Specification</dt>
				<dd property="w:specification"><a href="http://httpwg.org/specs/rfc7231.html#header.Accept-Encoding">RFC 7231: HTTP/1.1 Semantics and Content &#xA7;5.3.2. Accept-Encoding</a>, <a href="https://httpwg.org/specs/rfc7694.html">RFC 7694: HTTP Client-Initiated Content-Encoding</a></dd>
			</dl>

			<h2>Syntax</h2>
			<pre class="abnf-definition" w:space="indent">
				Accept-Encoding  = #( codings [ weight ] )
				codings          = content-coding / "identity" / "*"
				weight = OWS ";" OWS "q=" qvalue
				qvalue = ( "0" [ "." 0*3DIGIT ] )
				       / ( "1" [ "." 0*3("0") ] )
			</pre>

			<h2>Examples</h2>
			<p>Indicate support for compress, gzip:</p>
			<pre type="message/http">Accept-Encoding: compress, gzip</pre>

			<h2>Implementations</h2>
			<h3>Node.js</h3>
			<ul>
				<li>accepts</li>
				<li>negotiator</li>
			</ul>
		</main>
	</body>
</html>
