<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:w="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/"
	xmlns:xht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#"
>
	<head>
		<meta charset="UTF-8" />
		<title>308 Permanent Redirect</title>
		<meta name="description" content="The 308 Permanent Redirect HTTP status code tells clients to update references with the old URI, then re-issue the request at a different URI." />
		<link rel="up" href="index.xml" />
	</head>
	<body>
		<main about="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/http/status-codes/308" typeof="w:HTTP-StatusCode">
			<a rel="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#describedby" href="" />

			<h1>308 Permanent Redirect</h1>
			<p>The 308 Permanent Redirect HTTP status code tells clients the request was not filled, but the resource has been moved to another location; the client must update references with the old URI and re-issue the request at the new URI to complete the operation.</p>

			<h2>Writing responses (servers)</h2>
			<p>Servers should produce <code>308 Permanent Redirect</code> when a resource or set of resources has been assigned a new URI, especially one at a different authority/origin server.</p>
			<p>308 redirects can typically be configured as a search-and-replace on the request-URI.</p>
			<p>For a period of time, servers should instead issue <code>307 Temporary Redirect</code>, so that if there is an error in the redirect, it won't cause clients to adjust their bookmarks to a URI that doesn't exist.</p>

			<h2>Reading responses (clients)</h2>
			<p><code>308 Permanent Redirect</code> is an indication the client should adjust references to a different URI. If the client has any bookmarks, they should first be updated to the new URI.</p>
			<p>Then, the request should be re-tried at the URI.</p>
			<p>The server doesn't necessarily know anything about the target URI; the request at the redirect target might fail, but this doesn't change handling of the 308 response.</p>

			<h2>Overview table</h2>
			<dl class="inline">
				<dt>Name</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-value">308</dd>
				<dt>Message</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-line">308 Permanent Redirect</dd>
				<dt>Description</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-description">The resource has moved to a different URI and the request must be re-made.</dd>
				<dt>Specification</dt>
				<dd property="w:specification"><a href="https://httpwg.org/specs/rfc7538.html">RFC 7538: The Hypertext Transfer Protocol Status Code 308 (Permanent Redirect)</a></dd>
			</dl>

			<h2>Example</h2>
			<pre type="message/http" w:space="indent">
				HTTP/1.1 308 Permanent Redirect
			</pre>

			<!-- TODO: client support -->
			<h2>Implementations</h2>

			<h3>cURL</h3>
			<p>cURL correctly supports 308 redirects by following generic 300 semantics, if the response includes a Location header. It does not provide an explicit mechanism to rewrite or update URL references. A test for this status code was added in <a href="https://github.com/curl/curl/commit/f1092b387e1fa82db35c75a217bda91e94f0ee6e">cURL 7.24.0</a>.</p>

			<h3>Nginx</h3>
			<p>Nginx will send 308 Permanent Redirect when you use a rewrite rule with the <code>permanent</code> flag:</p>
			<pre w:space="indent">
				# Redirect www.example.com to example.com
				server {
					listen 80;
					server_name www.example.com;
				
					location / {
						rewrite  ^(/.*)  https://example.com$1  permanent;
					}
				}
			</pre>

			<h2>History</h2>
			<p>This status code largely replaces the <code>301 Moved Permanently</code> status code, which has a more ambiguous definition, and is inconsistently implemented by Web browsers. See the specification text for more information.</p>

		</main>
	</body>
</html>
