<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:w="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/"
	xmlns:xht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#"
>
	<head>
		<meta charset="UTF-8" />
		<title>410 Gone</title>
		<meta name="description" content="The 410 Gone HTTP status code indicates the resource was deleted and does not exist anymore." />
		<link rel="up" href="index.xml" />
	</head>
	<body>
		<main about="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/http/status-codes/410" typeof="w:HTTP-StatusCode">
			<a rel="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#describedby" href="" />

			<h1>410 Gone</h1>
			<p>The 410 (Gone) HTTP status code indicates the requested resource previously existed on the server, but no longer does. It is handled the same way as <a href="404.xml">404 (Not Found)</a>, but serves to reassure users that the resource has not disappeared by mistake.</p>
			<p>This status code is considered a 4xx client error because it is not a server error; the resource was deliberately removed and it is expected to be gone indefinitely.</p>

			<h2>Writing responses (servers)</h2>
			<p>This status code is a more specific variation of <a href="404.xml">404 Not Found</a> which implies the resource previously existed.</p>
			<p>If the resource was merely moved, servers should use <a href="308.xml">308 Permanent Redirect</a> instead.</p>

			<h3>Implementing with a Database</h3>
			<p>Implementing the 410 status code is most straightforward with a database that has a "deleted" flag. See <a href="#database-backed-applications">Database-backed applications</a> below.</p>

			<h3>Implementing with a filesystem</h3>
			<p>The simplest way to keep track of individual files that have been removed is to register them in a <code>.htaccess</code> file in the same directory (or similar file, if supported by your HTTP server), or else enter the file into the configuration file. See <i>Implementations</i> below for details.</p>
			<p>Most users settle for returning a 404 response.</p>

			<h2>Reading responses (clients)</h2>
			<p>This is the expected error code after a resource has been deleted by a client.</p>
			<p>Handling is similar to <a href="404.xml">404 Not Found</a>, see that status code for handling details.</p>

			<h2>Overview table</h2>
			<dl class="inline">
				<dt>Name</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-value">410</dd>
				<dt>Message</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-line">410 Gone</dd>
				<dt>Description</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-description">The resource was deleted and does not exist anymore</dd>
				<dt>Specification</dt>
				<dd property="w:specification"><a href="https://httpwg.org/specs/rfc7231.html#status.410">RFC 7231: HTTP/1.1 Semantics and Content &#xA7;6.5.9. 410 Gone</a></dd>
			</dl>

			<h2>Implementations</h2>
			
			<h3 id="database-backed-applications">Database-backed applications</h3>
			<p>Resources backed by a database may include a "deleted" flag to indicate the resource should no longer be accessible. An example SQL query:</p>
			<pre w:space="indent">
				SELECT deleted, data
				FROM documents
				WHERE id=?
			</pre>
			<p>
				If there are no results, return <code>404</code>. If the "deleted" flag on the returned result is nonzero, return <code>410</code>. Otherwise, continue processing the result towards a <code>200 OK</code> response.
			</p>

			<h3>Apache httpd</h3>
			<p>With mod_rewrite enabled, you may list regular expressions to file paths that will return 410 with the server-default error page. This may be used in a <code>.htaccess</code> file, if permitted by <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/mod/core.html#AllowOverride">AllowOverride</a>. The error document may be specified by <a href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.4/mod/core.html#errordocument">ErrorDocument</a>.</p>
			<pre w:space="indent">
				# G flag to set the status code to 410 Gone
				RewriteRule "index\.html$" "-" [G]
				ErrorDocument 410 /errors/removed.html
			</pre>
			
			<h3>Nginx</h3>
			<p>Use a <code>return</code> statement inside a <code>location</code> block to match patterns of files:</p>
			<pre w:space="indent">
				location /file/ {
					return 410;
				}
			</pre>
		</main>
	</body>
</html>
