<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:w="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/"
	xmlns:xht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#"
>
	<head>
		<meta charset="UTF-8" />
		<title>414 URI Too Long</title>
		<meta name="description" content="The 414 (URI Too Long) HTTP status code indicates the request URI is too long." />
		<link rel="up" href="index.xml" />
	</head>
	<body>
		<main about="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/http/status-codes/414" typeof="w:HTTP-StatusCode">
			<a rel="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#describedby" href="" />

			<h1>414 URI Too Long</h1>
			<p>The 414 URI Too Long HTTP status code indicates an unexpected or over-long request message body. In some environments, a lengthy request URI may trigger <a href="431.xml">431 Request Header Fields Too Large</a>, especially in HTTP/2, where the request-URI follws the same syntax as a header (see <i>Implementations</i> below).</p>

			<h2>Writing responses (servers)</h2>
			<p>On the Web and in HTTP, URIs are allowed to be indefinitely long; there is no defined limitation on URI length. However, at some point, long URIs can become technically infeasible, causing performance issues, excessive resource consumption, and can even be a vector for attacks against cryptographic systems if compressed over the wire. There are two triggers for this status code:</p>

			<h3>Parsing terminated</h3>
			<p>If the request-line is being parsed and the client has sent more characters than the server-defined maximum, terminate parsing, return <code>414 URI Too Long</code> with <code>Connection: close</code>, and close the stream.</p>

			<h3>Request fully parsed</h3>
			<p>If the server fully parsed the request headers, the server may still indicate one of the headers is too long to be used in processing the request.</p>


			<h2>Reading responses (clients)</h2>
			<p>The resource the client is trying to request probably does not exist, it does not make sense to re-try this request, but a request for a different resource could be considered instead.</p>

			<h2>Overview table</h2>
			<dl class="inline">
				<dt>Name</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-value">414</dd>
				<dt>Message</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-line">414 URI Too Long</dd>
				<dt>Description</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-description">The request URI is too large.</dd>
				<dt>Specification</dt>
				<dd property="w:specification"><a href="https://httpwg.org/specs/rfc7231.html#status.414">RFC 7231: HTTP/1.1 Semantics and Content &#xA7;6.5.12. 414 URI Too Long</a></dd>
			</dl>

			<h2>Example</h2>
			<pre type="message/http" w:space="indent">
				HTTP/1.1 414 URI Too Long
			</pre>

			<h2>Implementations</h2>
			<h3>Node.js</h3>
			<p>Node.js has a builtin HTTP parser that will respond if a header line exceeds the maximum allowed length. It treats the request-line the same as a header-line, see <a href="431.xml">431 Request Header Too Long</a> for setting this limit and generating a custom response when handling this error.</p>

			<h3>Apache HTTPD</h3>
			<p>Apache HTTPD returns <code>414 URI Too Long</code> when the total length of the request line, including HTTP method and version, but excluding the line terminator, is greater than the configured setting for <code>LimitRequestLine</code>, which defaults to 8190 bytes.</p>
			<p>See the <a href="https://httpd.apache.org/docs/trunk/mod/core.html#limitrequestline">LimitRequestLine Directive</a> and the <code>DEFAULT_LIMIT_REQUEST_LINE</code> constant for implementation details.</p>

			<!-- TODO: If there are any clients that can re-make a request with the correct Content-Type or Content-Encoding, list them here -->

			<h2>See also</h2>
			<ul>
				<li><a href="https://evertpot.com/http/414-uri-too-long">HTTP 414 by Evert Pot</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://httpstatusdogs.com/414-request-uri-too-long">HTTP 414 on HTTP STATUS DOGS</a></li>
			</ul>
		</main>
	</body>
</html>
