<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:w="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/"
	xmlns:xht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#"
>
	<head>
		<meta charset="UTF-8" />
		<title>503 Service Unavailable</title>
		<meta name="description" content="The 503 Service Unavailable HTTP status code indicates a temporary problem with the server that will likely improve after some delay." />
		<link rel="up" href="index.xml" />
	</head>
	<body>
		<main about="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/http/status-codes/503" typeof="w:HTTP-StatusCode">
			<a rel="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#describedby" href="" />

			<h1>503 Service Unavailable</h1>
			<p>The 503 (Service Unavailable) status code indicates a temporary problem with the server that will likely improve after some delay; for example, scheduled or unscheduled maintenance, or general overload.</p>

			<h2>Writing responses (servers)</h2>
			<p>Use this status code for things like scheduled maintenance, when the request queue is too long, or when the server is above CPU or I/O capacity.</p>
			<p>For alleviating very high capacity, the server may simply decide to refuse connections. Servers may have to balance this option against the possibility that clients do not implement exponential backoff, and immediately try to establish new connections.</p>
			<p>Servers should use the <a href="../headers/Retry-After.xml">Retry-After response header</a> with a sensible value. For an overload condition, values of a few seconds are sensible. If down for maintenance, values of 60-300 seconds are sensible. Think about the tasks that your users are likely trying to run, when picking a value.</p>
			<p>The response headers may include a <a href="../headers/Link.xml">Link header</a> with <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8631#section-6.4">rel=status</a> pointing to a service status page, that provides uptime, availability, and maintenance information.</p>
			<p>The response body should also include a link to the uptime or status page for the service, if any; and a description of a nature of the outage.</p>
			<p>Most load balancers can be configured to return this status code, to avoid forwarding requests to application servers while they are being worked on.</p>
			<p>If the request contains a long payload, consider <a href="../close.xml">terminating the request</a> to avoid consuming network resources.</p>

			<h3>See also: 507 (Insufficient Storage)</h3>
			<p>If the server can serve most requests, but it cannot accept incoming payloads because it has no storage to do so, see <a href="507.xml">507 (Insufficient Storage)</a>.</p>

			<h2>Reading responses (clients)</h2>
			<p>Clients may retry the request after the duration specified by the <a href="../headers/Retry-After.xml">Retry-After response header</a>; or else retry the request after a short period (e.g. one second), with exponential backoff for subsequent failed requests.</p>
			<p>If there is a response body, show it to the user, so they may make a decision about how to modify the request. For example, maybe there is important information about the scheduled maintenance window that the users can act on.</p>

			<h2>Overview table</h2>
			<dl class="inline">
				<dt>Name</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-value">503</dd>
				<dt>Message</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-line">503 Service Unavailable</dd>
				<dt>Description</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-description">Indicates a temporary problem with the server that will likely improve after a delay</dd>
				<dt>Specification</dt>
				<dd property="w:specification"><a href="https://httpwg.org/specs/rfc7231.html#status.503">RFC 7231: HTTP/1.1 Semantics and Content &#xA7;6.6.3. 503 Service Unavailable</a></dd>
			</dl>

			<h2>Example</h2>
			<pre type="message/http" w:space="indent">
				HTTP/1.0 503 Service Unavailable
				Retry-After: 3600
				Content-Type: text/plain
				Link: &lt;http://status.example.com/>;rel=status

				Our servers are currently down for scheduled maintenance.
				Maintenance begins Tue, 15 Nov 1994 08:12:31 GMT
				Estimated outage time: 6 hours
				Service status page: http://status.example.com/
			</pre>

			<!-- TODO: list implementations and how do you configure the page -->

		</main>
	</body>
</html>
