<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:w="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/">
	<head>
		<meta charset="UTF-8" />
		<title>Asynchronous Operations in HTTP</title>
		<meta name="description" content="Asynchronous Operations in HTTP" />
		<link rel="up" href="index.xml" />
	</head>
	<body>
		<main>
			<h1>Asynchronous Operations in HTTP</h1>

			<p>An <i>asynchronous operation</i> in HTTP is a request that the server will continue processing after the request returns, and can change the state of the server over time as the operation is being processed. This is in contrast to the typical "synchronous"  request whose effects, if any, do not occur after the response.</p>

			<p>Asynchronous operations are useful for any sort of operation that runs a very long time (which is anything than a few seconds for many applications), or when recovering from a network failure is important.</p>

			<p>Suppose a person owns a newfangled electric tea kettle running an HTTP server; how can other devices use this to listen for when the kettle is finished boiling water? We don't know quite when the task will complete; but we want to receive a message when the <i>operation</i> completes. This is called an <i>asynchronous operation</i> in HTTP.</p>

			<p>Use the "asynchronous operation workflow" when you need to support:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Receiving a notification when an operation finishes, e.g. when a tea kettle has finished boiling water</li>
				<li>Receiving a notification when an event happens, e.g. when a new blog post is published</li>
			</ul>

			<h2>Mechanisms for returning an Asynchronous Response</h2>
			<ul>
				<li><a href="preferences/respond-async.xml">Prefer: respond-async</a></li>
				<li><a href="status-codes/102.xml">102 (Processing)</a></li>
				<li><a href="status-codes/202.xml">202 (Accepted)</a></li>
				<li>Websockets</li>
				<li>Web Push</li>
				<li>Hook endpoints (Webhooks)</li>
				<li>Polling with exponential backoff</li>
				<li>Long polling</li>
				<li>Email</li>
			</ul>

			<h2>Glossary</h2>
			<dl>
				<dt>Event</dt><dd>A change in the state of the service, that a user may wish to know about as soon as possible.</dd>
				<dt>Service</dt><dd>The party that is typically the server; but may use a client when delivering a notification to a user of the service.</dd>
				<dt>User</dt><dd>The party that is typically the client; but may also run a server in order to receive notifications from the service.</dd>
				<dt>Request</dt><dd>A standard HTTP request that synchronously returns a response; the request may kick off new operations and subscriptions that run after the request has returned.</dd>
				<dt>Operation</dt><dd>A request by a user for the service to perform a task; that may generate events until the operation completes.</dd>
				<dt>Notification</dt><dd>A message that a service wants to deliver to a user, conveying newly available information.</dd>
				<dt>Subscription</dt><dd>A request by a user to receive notifications from a service, until the user decides to stop listening.</dd>
			</dl>

			<h2>Mechanisms for real-time notifications</h2>
			<p>The simplest mechanism is to make the results of the operation available from a resource that the user must poll: re-request until the resource says the operation is complete.</p>
			<p>The other way to receive a <i>notification</i> from the service. The user must either run a server listening for a message, or the user must connect to a service where they may receive an message in real time.</p>
			<dl>
				<dt>Websockets</dt>
				<dd>A datagram protocol specifically designed for shuttling arbitrary messages asynchronously, tunneled over HTTP.</dd>

				<dt>Web Push</dt>
				<dd>A protocol optimized for sending notifications to mobile devices.</dd>

				<dt>Hook endpoints (Webhooks)</dt>
				<dd>A technique where a user registers a URL endpoint with a service, with which notifications are delivered using a POST request to that endpoint. Implementations must be careful to check the authenticity of notifications, since the endpoint is typically accessible on the public Internet.</dd>

				<dt>Polling with exponential backoff</dt>
				<dd>The first purely-HTTP method of checking for updates. This is typically combined with <a href="headers/If-Modified-Since.xml">If-Modified-Since</a> to only receive a response if the server has new information to be read.</dd>

				<dt>Long polling</dt>
				<dd>A technique where an HTTP server waits to respond to a request until it has new information. This may be implemented with <a href="headers/If-Modified-Since.xml">If-Modified-Since</a> and a header that specifies to wait until there is an update that permits a 200 OK response, or some status besides 304 Not Modified.</dd>

				<dt>Email</dt>
				<dd>Perhaps the oldest and most well known real-time notification mechanism. Email supports sending signed machine-readable documents, but is typically used for sending formatted messages for people to read.</dd>
			</dl>

			<h3>Status Codes</h3>
			<p>This is an overview on how clients should handle status codes relating to an operation they requested.</p>
			<p>What important distinctions does a client need to know about?</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Operation finished</li>
				<li>Operation successful</li>
				<li>Operation result URI with additional information about the request</li>
			</ul>
			<table>
				<thead>
					<tr><th>Status Code</th><th>Complete</th><th>Successful</th></tr>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<tr><th>200 OK</th><td>Yes✅</td><td>Yes✅</td></tr>
					<tr><th>201 Created</th><td>Yes✅</td><td>Yes✅</td></tr>
					<tr><th>202 Accepted</th><td>No👎</td><td>Indeterminate</td></tr>
					<tr><th>303 See Other</th><td>Yes✅</td><td>Unknown</td></tr>
				</tbody>
			</table>

			<h2>Examples/Implementations</h2>
			<ul>
				<li><a href="https://developer.github.com/webhooks/">GitHub's Webhooks</a></li>
			</ul>
			<aside><p>If you know of additional examples, please add or submit them.</p></aside>

			<h2>See also</h2>
			<ul>
				<li><a href="https://requestbin.com/blog/working-with-webhooks/">RequestBin: Webhooks — The Definitive Guide</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8030">Generic Event Delivery Using HTTP Push</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8291">Message Encryption for Web Push</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc8292">Voluntary Application Server Identification (VAPID) for Web Push</a></li>
				<li><a href="https://w3c.github.io/push-api/">Push API</a></li>
			</ul>
		</main>
	</body>
</html>
