<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:w="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/"
	xmlns:xht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#"
>
	<head>
		<meta charset="UTF-8" />
		<title>404 Not Found</title>
		<meta name="description" content="The 404 (Not Found) HTTP status code indicates the resource does not exist." />
		<link rel="up" href="index.xml" />
	</head>
	<body>
		<main about="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/http/status-codes/404" typeof="w:HTTP-StatusCode">
			<a rel="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#describedby" href="" />

			<h1>404 Not Found</h1>
			<p>The 404 (Not Found) HTTP status code indicates the requested resource was not found, and no such error is known.</p>
			<p>This is a 4xx client error because it is typically generated by clients who fill out URI templates (such as HTML forms) with names that do not exist. It might be a server error if the record is merely missing, and needs to be restored, as is the case with broken links.</p>

			<h2>Writing responses (servers)</h2>
			<p>This status code is used in response to methods that expect the request-URI to exist on the server, when the resource does not exist. This typically includes safe methods, and other methods that require a resource; including GET, HEAD, OPTIONS, and POST.</p>
			<p>This status might also be used when disclosing the existence of a resource to an unauthorized user could be a security or privacy problem. If used for this purpose, authorization should be tested immediately after the resource is dereferenced, and before handling for <code>405 Method Not Allowed</code>, <code>410 Gone</code>, <code>429 Too Many Requests</code>, and so on, so that the behavior is the same as the resource truly not existing.</p>
			<p>Servers responding with this error code may wish to log the <a href="../headers/Referer.xml">Referer header</a>, if any, which can be used to troubleshoot the presence of broken links.</p>
			<p>If the resource has merely been deleted (for example, a "deleted" flag on the database record is set), then see <a href="410.xml">410 Gone</a> instead.</p>
			<p>Servers may wish to keep track of links and a record of link targets that do not exist. If the request is for one of these resources, the server should provide instructions on how to create the resource, using a link rel=create-form, and should advertise the ability for clients to create the resource directly using an <code><a href="../headers/Allow.xml">Allow</a>: PUT</code> header.</p>
			<p>The exact contents of this error will likely vary by the namespace that the URI falls under. For example, a server might reserve URIs beginning with <code>http://example.com/~</code> for usernames; so when handling requests for users that do not exist, the server may opt to theme 404 responses in a different HTML theme than the rest of the website.</p>

			<h2>Reading responses (clients)</h2>
			<p>A <code>404 Not Found</code> or <code><a href="410.xml">410 Gone</a></code> response indicates that the resource was not found on the server. Clients that want to know if the resource exists or not should check both of these status codes.</p>
			<p>If the client found this resource from a link on another page, it may be an invitation for the client to create the resource. Otherwise, the user may want to inform the server operator of a broken link.</p>
			<p>If the client generated the URI from a URI template (such as an HTML form), it means the server has not created a resource with the specified parameters yet; the client may try creating the given resource using a PUT request.</p>
			<p>Some servers are known to hide the existence of resources until a user is sufficiently authorized to view the resource. If the server is known to require credentials, verify that the credentials work before trying other error recovery options.</p>

			<h2>Overview table</h2>
			<dl class="inline">
				<dt>Name</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-value">404</dd>
				<dt>Message</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-line">404 Not Found</dd>
				<dt>Description</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-StatusCode-description">The resource does not exist</dd>
				<dt>Specification</dt>
				<dd property="w:specification"><a href="https://httpwg.org/specs/rfc7231.html#status.404">RFC 7231: HTTP/1.1 Semantics and Content &#xA7;6.5.4. 404 Not Found</a></dd>
			</dl>

		</main>
	</body>
</html>
