<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:w="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/"
	xmlns:xht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#"
>
	<head>
		<meta charset="UTF-8" />
		<title>Content-Encoding</title>
		<meta name="description" content="Specifies how to decode/decompress the message body into the intended media type" />
		<link rel="up" href="index.xml" />
	</head>
	<body>
		<main about="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/http/headers/Content-Encoding" typeof="w:HTTP-Header">
			<a rel="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#describedby" href="" />

			<h1>Content-Encoding</h1>
			<p>The <code>Content-Encoding</code> header lists any <i>codings</i> used to encode the document into the message body. A content encoding is typically preserved end-to-end, and metadata headers (e.g. <code>Content-Length</code>) describe this encoded message.</p>
			<p>Codings are listed innermost to outermost. Content-Encoding is the last transformation to be decoded before the document is parsed according to its media type semantics, after <a href="Transfer-Encoding.xml">Transfer-Coding</a> and <a href="Content-Length.xml">Content-Length</a>.</p>

			<h2>Writing requests (clients)</h2>
			<p>Clients may find it desirable to compress an request message body. Clients should send <code>Expect: 100-continue</code> so the server can verify it's able to read the listed coding.</p>
			<p>If the server is not able to read the selected content coding, it will respond with <a href="../status-codes/415.xml">415 Unsupported Media Type</a>; re-try the request according to the directions for handling that status code.</p>

			<h2>Reading requests (servers)</h2>
			<p>If the server does not understand any of the listed codings, return <code>415 (Unsupported Media Type)</code> and describe the acceptable coding types in a response. Use an HTML or plain text document to describe the error; there is currently no standard, machine-readable way to list acceptable coding types for clients.</p>

			<h2>Writing responses (servers)</h2>
			<p>If the client specified a list of acceptable content-encodings in the <a href="Accept-Encoding.xml">Accept-Encoding</a> request header, then select one of them, apply it to the response body, and list it in <code>Content-Encoding</code>.</p>

			<h2>Reading responses (clients)</h2>
			<p>If the client does not understand any of the listed codings, re-try the request with an <a href="Accept-Encoding.xml">Accept-Encoding</a> header. Requests without an <code>Accept-Encoding</code> header can be sent with the server's choice of coding.</p>

			<h2>Overview table</h2>
			<dl class="inline">
				<dt>Name</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Header-name">Content-Encoding</dd>
				<dt>Description</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Header-description">Lists the transformations applied to the message body.</dd>
				<dt>Direction</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Header-direction">Both</dd>
				<dt>Negotiated by</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Header-negotiated-by" resource="w:http/headers/Accept-Encoding"><a href="Accept-Encoding.xml">Accept-Encoding</a></dd>
				<dt>Specification</dt>
				<dd property="w:specification"><a href="https://httpwg.org/specs/rfc7231.html#header.content-encoding">RFC 7230: HTTP/1.1 Caching &#xA7;6.1. Content-Encoding</a></dd>
			</dl>

			<h2>Syntax</h2>
			<pre type="abnf" w:space="indent">
				Content-Encoding = 1#content-coding
			</pre>
			<p>Content-Encoding options are case-insensitive. For clarity, connection options are written in lowercase, and header names are typically written in their typical title case.</p>
			<h3>Example</h3>
			<pre type="message/http">Content-Encoding: gzip</pre>
		</main>
	</body>
</html>
