<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" dir="ltr"
	xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
	xmlns:w="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/"
	xmlns:xht="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#"
>
	<head>
		<meta charset="UTF-8" />
		<title>PATCH</title>
		<meta name="description" content="PATCH modifies the target resource according to the given instructions" />
		<link rel="up" href="index.xml" />
	</head>
	<body>
		<main about="tag:fullstack.wiki,2018:ns/http/methods/PATCH" typeof="w:HTTP-Method">
			<a rel="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml/vocab#describedby" href="" />

			<h1>PATCH</h1>
			<p>The PATCH allows a client to modify a resource according to provided instructions. This can include a applying a diff.</p>

			<h2>Writing requests (clients)</h2>
			<p>If a client wants to modify a specific part of a resource without overwriting the entire document, it should use the PATCH method with a media type that can express the desired change; if this is available on the server.</p>
			<p>If applicable, send the request with a <a href="../conditional.xml">conditional test (e.g. If-Match)</a>, to avoid creating the resource in the event it does not exist.</p>
			<p>Check the error code and follow the error recovery process, <a href="../status-codes/405.xml">405 (Method Not Allowed)</a>, <a href="../status-codes/415.xml">415 (Unsupported Media Type)</a>, or <a href="../status-codes/501.xml">501 (Not Implemented)</a> may require that the request be retried with an equivelant PUT request.</p>

			<h2>Reading requests (servers)</h2>
			<p>Servers that use <a href="../status-codes/428.xml">428 (Precondition Required)</a> should judge if the patch media-type has sufficient information to avoid lost updates. If the patch can only be applied if the document is in an expected state, then the server should not require a precondition header, since this would be redundant.</p>
			<p>Check the <a href="../preferences/return.xml">"return"</a> preference for guidence on what response should be generated. By default, return a short document summarizing the changes made.</p>

			<h2>Overview table</h2>
			<dl class="inline">
				<dt>Name</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Method-name">PATCH</dd>
				<dt>Description</dt>
				<dd property="w:HTTP-Method-description">Modifies the target resource according to the given instructions.</dd>
				<dt>Specification</dt>
				<dd property="w:specification"><a href="https://httpwg.org/specs/rfc5789.html">RFC 5789: PATCH Method for HTTP</a></dd>
			</dl>
		</main>
	</body>
</html>
